Control flow features let you write code that takes one action in some situations and another action in different situations. They're how you express decisions in your code.
控制流功能让你的代码在某种情况采取一种操作，在另一种情况时采取另一种操作。它们是你在代码中表达决策的方式。
In this module, we're going to cover if, else if, and else; three different kinds of loops – loop, while, and for; and the match expression. We'll be defining and calling functions in this module,
在本节中，我们将介绍if、else if 和 else；三种不同的循环：loop、while 和 for；以及匹配表达式。我们将在本节中定义和调用函数，
so check out the previous module on functions
所以如果你需要复习的话，
if you need to review.
请查看前面的函数一节。
Let's start with if, else if, and else. We can write code that only uses if by starting with the if keyword, then an expression that evaluates to a Boolean, then curly brackets containing the code that should run if the condition evaluates to true.
让我们从 if、else if 和 else 开始。我们可以编写只使用 if 的代码，方法是以 if 关键字开头，然后是一个结果为 boolean 的表达式，然后是大括号，里面包含如果 boolean 表达式如果为真是要执行的代码。
If the condition evaluates to false,
如果条件为假，
the code in the brackets won't get run.
大括号里的代码就不会执行。
Optionally, you can have an else block that goes with an if block that contains code to run
可选的 ，你还可以使用 else 块以和 if 块一起使用，
if the condition evaluates to false.
else 块的代码会在条件表达式为假的时候执行。
You can also have multiple conditions by having an if block, then an else if
你也可以使用多个条件判断，通过一个 if 代码块和
block with another condition,
一个 else if 代码块，
as many else if blocks as you want,
再然后是任意多的 else if 代码块，
and then an optional else block that is run
再然后是可选的 else 代码块，
if all of the conditions evaluate to false.
如果上面所有的条件判断都为假，这个 else 代码块就会执行。
Like with functions, we can get a value from an if or else block by leaving the semicolon off of the last expression in the block.
和函数一样，我们可以从 if 或 else 代码块中得到一个值，方法是在该块里的最后一个表达式不加分号。
We can then put that value in a variable.
然后我们就可以把这个值放到一个变量中。
Note,
注意，
we do need a semicolon to end the variable assignment statement.
我们确实需要一个分号来结束变量赋值语句。
This code prints
这段代码会打印
Your discount is 50!.
Your discount is 50!.
Note that when we return a value from an if else expression for a variable,
请注意，当我们从一个变量的 if else 表达式中返回一个值时，
there must be an else clause so that the variable always gets a value. And the types of the values must all be the same –
必须有一个 else 子句，以便该变量总是能得到一个值。而且这些值的类型必须相同，
in this case,
在本例中是 i32。
Next,
接下来，
let's talk about loops.
我们谈谈 loop 循环。
Loops let you run the same code repeatedly.
loop 循环让你重复运行相同的代码。
The loop keyword lets you specify a block of code that should be run forever.
loop 关键字可以指定一段永远运行的代码块。
This loop prints hello, world!
这个例子里的循环会反复打印 hello,world!
This program will run until the end of time.
这段代码永不会停止运行。
We've stopped it using Ctrl +C.
我们得使用 Ctrl+C 来停止它。
You can use the break keyword to exit a loop.
你可以使用 break 关键字来退出 loop 循环。
This code will loop forever,
这个例子会一直循环，
asking What's the secret word?
会打印 What's the secret word?
and waiting for input, unless you type in the correct secret word, rust. In that case, we'll break out of the loop.
并等待输入，除非你输入了正确的密码：rust。在这种情况下，程序会跳出循环。
When we run this program and type java, the loop asks us again,
当我们运行这个程序，并输入 java，循环会再次询问，
and if we type rust,
当我们输入 rust 时，
the code breaks out of the loop and the program ends.
代码就会跳出循环，程序就会结束。
The code we've written here,
这里的代码我们用的是
using loop, if, and break, could also be written using a while loop.
loop、if 和 break，也可以使用 while 循环。
A while loop is written with the while keyword, then an expression that evaluates to true or false, then curly brackets and a block of code.
while 循环语法是用 while 关键字，然后一个结果为 true 或 flase 的表达式，然后是大括号和一个代码块。
The code in the block runs over and over,
当指定的表达式为真时，
while the expression specified is true.
该块中的代码就会反复运行。
Here's the secret word example rewritten using a while loop.
这里是一个使用 while 循环的密语例子。
It works exactly the same, but is a little bit more concise.
它和刚才 loop 例子的结果完全一致，但更简洁一些。
The condition for when the loop should exit is now part of the start of the loop,
循环何时退出的条件现在是循环开始的一部分，
rather than inside the loop somewhere.
而不是循环里的某个地方。
The for loop is probably the most common loop in Rust code.
for 循环可能是 Rust 代码中最常见的循环。
It lets you run some code for each item in a collection.
它可以让你为集合中的每个条目运行一些代码。
Unlike for loops in some other languages, like C,
不像其他语言中的 for 循环，比如 C 语言，
you don't need to manage an index into the collection and worry about
你不需要管理集合的索引，也不需要
off-by-one errors.
担心差一错误（off-by-one errors)。
To write a for loop, use the for keyword,
要写 for 循环，使用 for 关键字，
then pick a variable name to use inside the loop body to refer to each individual item. Then, put the keyword in, and specify the collection you want to use.
然后选一个变量名，以指代每次循环中集合中的某一项。然后，写上 in 关键字和你要遍历的集合。
Then, put curly brackets and the code that should be run for each item.
然后，加上大括号和为每个条目要执行的代码。
Here, for the collection, we're using the range syntax – two dots – to create a range of integers,
这个例子中，对于这个集合，我们使用范围语法：两个点，来创建一个整数范围，
starting from 1 inclusive and ending before 11.
从 1 到 11（不包括）。
For each number in the range, the for loop will print Now serving numberwith the number of the current iteration through the loop.
对于这个范围内的每个数字，for 循环将会打印 Now serving number 和当前循环的这个数字。
We can see that this code starts by printing Now serving number 1, and ends with printing Now serving number 10.
我们可以看到这段代码以打印 Now serving number 1 开始，以 Now serving number 10 结束。
Finally,
最后，
let's talk about match expressions.
让我们来谈谈匹配表达式，
match isn't something very many programming languages have.
匹配语句（译者注：不翻译直接用 match更好）不是一个很多编程语言都有的东西。
It's sort of like a bunch of
它有点像一堆
if/else ifs and sort of like a switch
if/else if 语句，也稍微有点像
or case
switch-case 语句，
but better for two reasons:
但有两个比它们更好的原因：
pattern matching and exhaustiveness checking.
模式匹配和穷举检查。
First,
首先，
let's talk about pattern matching.
让我们来谈谈模式匹配。
Pattern matching is a feature available in Rust in multiple places.
模式匹配是 Rust 中多个地方都有的功能。
We actually used pattern matching when we destructured a tuple into parts
实际上在数据类型一节，我们已经使用了模式匹配来将元组分解成
in the Data types module. Surprise!
若干部分。真是一个惊喜！
Pattern matching is especially useful in match expressions.
模式匹配在匹配表达式中特别有用。
We specify a list of patterns to test a value against, and the match expression tests the value against each pattern and stops if it finds a matching one.
我们指定一个模式列表来测试一个值，匹配表达式根据每个模式检测这个值，如果找到一个匹配的模式就停止。
Then, it runs the code that goes with that pattern.
然后就运行和该模式匹配的代码。
Here's an example of a match expression.
下面是一个匹配表达式的例子。
We have an integer stored in the variable x,
我们在变量 x 中存储了一个整数，
and we want to match x against some patterns.
然后用 x 和一些模式进行匹配。
In this case,
在这个例子中，
the patterns are literal numbers.
这些模式都是数字字面量。
What Rust does is it takes x,
Rust 做的是将 x，
which in this case is 3, and compares it to 1, which doesn't match.
本例子中是 3，与 1 进行比较，并不匹配。
So, it moves on to the next pattern,
因此接着继续和下一个模式，2，去比较，
which also doesn't match, onto the next pattern,
也不匹配，接下来是 3，
which does match.
这次匹配上了。
So Rust will print, Three's a crowd, and be done with this match expression.
因此这里会打印 Thres's a crowed，并结束这段匹配表达式。
The underscore in the last pattern is a catch-all that will match any value. So the last arm functions like an else in a set of
模式列表中的最后一个项，下划线，代表匹配任何值。所以最后一项的功能就像 if/else if/else 代码块中的
if/else
else 的一样。
There are lots of different ideas you can express with pattern matching.
有很多不同的想法可以用模式匹配来表达。
This example shows some logic that might be used in a board game where you roll two dice.
比如这个例子展示了一些逻辑，可能会用在两个骰子弹棋盘游戏中。
We've hardcoded the values of the dice roll to simplify this example.
为了简化这个例子，我们对骰子的值进行了硬编码。
The first arm matches a roll where both dice have the value 1. The second arm matches
match 里面第一行匹配的是两个骰子都是1的情况。第二行匹配
any roll where
两个骰子中
one of the two dice is 5,
某一个是 5 的情况，
but it doesn't matter which one, and we use underscores in the tuple pattern to ignore any other value.
但具体是哪个并不重要，我们在元祖模式中使用下划线来忽略这个位置上的值。
The vertical bar between the two patterns means or. Also note that we can have multiple lines of code paired with the pattern by putting curly brackets around them.
两个模式之间的竖线表示逻辑或。还要注意的是，我们可以在某个模式里加上大括号，让多行代码与模式配对。（译者注：说得这么啰嗦，就是匹配该模式后可以用大括号来执行多行代码）
Again, the last pattern is an underscore that will match any value for the whole tuple that hasn't already been matched.
同样的，最后一个模式这里又是一个下划线，它将匹配元祖的任何值，任何上面都没匹配成功的情况。
This code prints,
这段代码会打印出，
You rolled at least one 5! Move and
You rolled at least one 5!Move and
then roll again!.
then roll again!.
The other reason match expressions are awesome is that they must be exhaustive and cover every case.
匹配表达式另一个很棒的点是，它们必须穷尽地覆盖了每一种情况。
This prevents bugs that can be caused by forgetting to handle a situation.
这可以防止因忘记处理某种情况而引起的错误。
For example,
例如，
here's a match statement where we're checking two Booleans:
这里有一个 match 语句，我们要检查两个布尔值：
is_confirmed and is_active.
is_confirmed 和 is_active。
We've forgotten the case
这里我们忘记了
where is_confirmed is true and is_active is false.
is_confirmed 为 true，is_active 为 false 的情况。
If we try to compile this, Rust
如果我们尝试编译这段代码，
can see that we haven't covered every possibility. In this case,
Rust 会提示我们没有覆盖所有可能性。在这个例子中，
it's even able to tell us which case we missed –
编译器甚至能够告诉我们缺少了哪种情况。
thanks,
谢谢你，
Rust!
Rust!
We would fix this either by adding the explicit case we missed or by using an underscore to explicitly acknowledge that we want to ignore all other cases.
我们可以通过明确添加缺少的情况，或者通过使用下划线来显式指出我们就是要忽略其他情况来解决这个问题。
In this module, we've covered the if/else
在本节中，我们介绍了了 if、else if、
if/else construct that conditionally runs blocks of code;
else 结构，这种结构会有条件地运行代码块；
the loop keyword that runs a block repeatedly
loop 关键字，它会永远重复运行代码块；
forever; the while loop that runs code
while 循环，它在条件为真的时候
while a condition is true;
重复运行代码；
the for loop that iterates over each element in a collection; and the match expression that uses pattern matching and has exhaustiveness checking to handle all possibilities a value might be.
for 循环，它在一个集合中迭代每个元素；以及匹配表达式，它使用模式匹配和穷举检查来处理一个值的所有可能情况。
These are the building blocks of complex logic.
以上这些是构建复杂逻辑所需要的。
Next module,
下一节，
let's explore enums – a way to define a custom type that works nicely with match expressions.
让我们来探索枚举——一种定义自定义类型的方法，可以很好地与匹配表达式一起工作。